<?xml version="1.0"?>
<OLAC_doc>
  <header>
	 <status code="adopted" type="recommendation"/>
	 <!-- Promoted to Adopted on 2008-12-19 -->
	<title>OLAC Role Vocabulary</title>
	<baseName>role</baseName>
	<issued>20060406</issued>
	<previousIssued>20031010</previousIssued>
	<abstract>
	  <p>Role is an attribute of both the Creator and Contributor elements. (Please note that Dublin
	  Core now discourages the use of the Creator element, recommending that all Role information be
	  associated with Contributor elements.) This document specifies the controlled vocabulary of the
	  Role attribute used by OLAC. This attribute specifies the functional role of the entity named
	  in the creation of a given resource.</p>
	</abstract>
	<editors>
		  Heidi Johnson (<url>mailto:ailla@ailla.org</url>)
		</editors>
	<copyright>
		  Heidi Johnson (University of Texas at Austin)
		</copyright>
	<changes>
	  <p>Promoted to candidate status, with a call for review by
		those who have put the document into practice.</p>
	</changes>
  </header>
  <body>
	<section>
	  <heading>Introduction</heading>
	  <p>Key points: multiple choices are allowed for a single participant.</p>
	</section>
	<section>
	  <heading>Role</heading>
	  <p>Each term of the controlled vocabulary is described in one of the
		following subsections. The heading gives the encoded value for the term that is
		to be used as the value of the <i>code</i> attribute of the <i>Contributor</i> metadata
		element <cit>OLAC-Metadata</cit>. Under the heading, the term is described in four ways.
		<i>Name</i> gives a descriptive label for the term. <i>Definition</i> is a one-line summary
		of what the term means.
		<i>Comments</i>  offers more details on what the term represents, and may also include
		 examples given to illustrate how the term is meant to be applied.</p>
		<p>Additional roles may be found in the MARC Relator set <cit>MARC-RELATOR</cit>. Any MARC
		 term that does not appear in the OLAC Roles set defined below may be used in the sense
		 defined in the MARC document. The roles defined here are either very commonly used to
		 characterize the creators of linguistic resources, or have been re-defined to reflect
		 specifically linguistic practice. Some examples of MARC Relator terms that may be used
		 without modification are 'copyright_holder','artist', 'metadata_contact', 'director',
		 and 'calligrapher'.</p>
	  <term>
		<code>annotator</code>
		<name>Annotator</name>
		<definition>The participant produced an annotation of this or a related
		 resource.</definition>
	  </term>
	  <term>
		<code>author</code>
		<name>Author</name>
		<definition>The participant contributed original writings to the resource.</definition>
	  </term>
	  <term>
		<code>careful_speech_speaker</code>
		<name>Careful Speech Speaker</name>
		<definition>The participant carefully re-speaks the words recorded in an source recording.</definition>
	  </term>
	  <term>
		<code>compiler</code>
		<name>Compiler</name>
		<definition>The participant is responsible for collecting the sub-parts of the
		resource together.</definition>
		<comment>
		  <p>This refers to someone who creates a <i>single</i> resource with multiple
					parts, such as a book of short stories, or a person who
					produces a corpus of resources, which may be archived separately.</p>
		</comment>
		<examples><p>A compiler of a book of short stories or a CD with several songs on it;
		  a collector of a corpus of recordings in some language or on a given topic;
		  a person who assembles a suite of software tools.</p>
		</examples>
	  </term>
	  <term>
		<code>consultant</code>
		<name>Consultant</name>
		<definition>The participant contributes expertise to the creation of a work.</definition>
		<comment>
		  <p>This term is commonly used by field linguists for the native speakers who work with
		  them in describing and analyzing a language.  They contribute their expertise in their
		  native language to the resource, although their speech, sign, or writing may not appear
		  directly in  the resource. In some parts of the world the preferred term for this role is
		  "informant".</p>
		</comment>
	  </term>
	  <term>
		<code>data_inputter</code>
		<name>Data Inputter</name>
		<definition>The participant was responsible for entering, re-typing, and/or structuring the data
			  contained in the resource.</definition>
	  </term>
	  <term>
		<code>depositor</code>
		<name>Depositor</name>
		<definition>The participant was responsible for depositing the resource in an archive.</definition>
	  </term>
	  <term>
		<code>developer</code>
		<name>Developer</name>
		<definition>The participant developed the methodology or tools that constitute the resource,
		or that were used to create the resource.</definition>
		<examples><p>A software programmer, designer, or analyst; a designer of a questionnaire
		or research task.
		</p></examples>
	  </term>
	  <term>
		<code>editor</code>
		<name>Editor</name>
		<definition>The participant reviewed, corrected, and/or tested the resource.</definition>
		<comment>
		  <p>This role includes anyone whose role was editorial in nature, such as proof-readers,
					debuggers, testers, etc.  It may overlap the Compiler role in some cases.</p>
		</comment>
	  </term>
	  <term>
		<code>illustrator</code>
		<name>Illustrator</name>
		<definition>The participant contributed drawings or other illustrations to the resource.</definition>
	  </term>
	  <term>
		<code>interpreter</code>
		<name>Interpreter</name>
		<definition>The participant translates in real-time or explains the discourse recorded in the resource.</definition>
		<comment>
			<p> The choice between 'interpreter' and 'translator' may depend on the dynamics of the resource creation
		  event or process. Generally, if the participant is translating 'live'; that is, while the speaker or signer is
		  speaking or signing, she or he should be identified as an interpreter. Also, some discourse genres include a
		  participant who interprets or explains a performance of some kind.</p></comment>
		<examples><p>A person translating from English to ASL during a speech; a Kuna chief who interprets a chant that
		  another chief has just performed, thus completing the ceremony.</p></examples>
	  </term>
	  <term>
		<code>interviewer</code>
		<name>Interviewer</name>
		<definition>The participant conducted an interview that forms part of the resource.</definition>
	  </term>
      <term>
        <code>oral_translation_speaker</code>
        <name>Oral Translation Speaker</name>
        <definition>A general translator who was helping when the session was recorded.</definition>
      </term>
	  <term>
		<code>participant</code>
		<name>Participant</name>
		<definition>The participant was present during the creation of the resource, but did not
		contribute substantially to its content.</definition>
		<comment>
		  <p>This role is intended for minor participants such as audience members or other peripherally-involved
		  participants in the event.  These interlocutors need not have been physically present.  They could be
		  participants in some form of long-distance communication, such as lurkers in an online discussion, or they
		  may have participated in the general sense of having allowed the event to take place, such as the
		  mayor of an indigenous community.</p>
		</comment>
	  </term>
	  <term>
		<code>performer</code>
		<name>Performer</name>
		<definition>The participant performed some portion of a recorded, filmed, or transcribed resource.</definition>
		<comment>
		  <p>It is recommended that this term be used only for creative participants whose role is not better
		  indicated by a more specific term, such as 'speaker', 'signer', or 'singer'. </p></comment>
		<examples><p>A person performing a ceremony or delivering an oration or a sermon; native speakers
		  re-enacting a traditional genre of speech, such as ritual greetings or insults; an actor or musician.</p>
		</examples>
	  </term>
	  <term>
		<code>photographer</code>
		<name>Photographer</name>
		<definition>The participant took the photograph, or shot the film, that appears in or
				constitutes the resource.</definition>
	  </term>
	  <term>
		<code>recorder</code>
		<name>Recorder</name>
		<definition>The participant operated the recording machinery used to create the resource.</definition>
	  </term>
	  <term>
		<code>researcher</code>
		<name>Researcher</name>
		<definition>The resource was created as part of the participant's research, or the research
		presents interim or final results from the participant's research.</definition>
	  </term>
	  <term>
		<code>research_participant</code>
		<name>Research Participant</name>
		<definition>The participant acted as a research subject or responded to a questionnaire, the
				results of which study form the basis of the resource.</definition>
	  </term>
	  <term>
		<code>responder</code>
		<name>Responder</name>
		<definition>The participant was an interlocutor in some sort of discourse event.
		</definition>
		<comment><p>This person's voice can be  heard (or their words can be read)
		  in the resource, typically saying the
		  language-appropriate equivalent of "uh-huh", "amen", "you don't say", etc.
		  This role is sometimes referred
		  to as a "yes-sayer", "backchanneler, or "co-conversant".
		</p></comment>
	  </term>
	  <term>
		<code>signer</code>
		<name>Signer</name>
		<definition>The participant was a principal signer in a resource that consists of a
				recording, a film, or a transcription of a recorded resource.</definition>
		<comment>
		  <p>Signers are those whose gestures predominate in a recorded or filmed
		  resource. (This resource may be a transcription of that recording.)</p></comment>
		<examples><p>Participants in a recorded conversation, elicitation session, or informal
		  narration would be termed Signers.  Audience members who do not participate
		  beyond the occasional backchannel would be termed Responders.
		</p></examples>
	  </term>
	  <term>
		<code>singer</code>
		<name>Singer</name>
		<definition>The participant sang, either individually or as part of a group, in
			a resource that consists of a recording, a film, or a transcription of a recorded
			resource.
		</definition>
	  </term>
	  <term>
		<code>speaker</code>
		<name>Speaker</name>
		<definition>The participant was a principal speaker in a resource that consists of a
				recording, a film, or a  transcription of a recorded resource.</definition>
		<comment>
		  <p>Speakers are those whose voices predominate in a recorded or filmed
		  resource. (This resource may be a transcription of that recording.) </p>
		  <p>Examples: Participants in a recorded conversation, elicitation session, or informal
		  narration would be termed Speakers.  Audience members who do not participate
		  beyond the occasional backchannel would be termed Responders.</p>
		</comment>
	  </term>
	  <term>
		<code>sponsor</code>
		<name>Sponsor</name>
		<definition>The participant contributed financial support to the creation of the resource.</definition>
	  </term>
	  <term>
		<code>transcriber</code>
		<name>Transcriber</name>
		<definition>The participant produced a transcription of this or a related resource.</definition>
	  </term>
	  <term>
		<code>translator</code>
		<name>Translator</name>
		<definition>The participant produced a translation of this or a related resource.</definition>
	  </term>
	</section>
  </body>

  <todo>
	<p>
	  Elicit roles from language researchers other than documentary linguists.
	</p>
  </todo>

  <references>
	<ref abbrev="OLAC-Metadata">OLAC Metadata<br/>
	  &lt;<url>http://www.language-archives.org/OLAC/metadata.html</url>></ref>
	<ref abbrev="MARC-RELATOR">MARC Relator Terms.<br/>
	  &lt;<url>http://www.loc.gov/marc/relators/relators.html</url>></ref>
  </references>
</OLAC_doc>
